Williams, Jonathan mss., 1738-1869. LMC 2441
Lilly Library
Williams, Jonathan mss.
1738-1869
Lilly Library
Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815.
LMC 2441
7203 Items
The Williams, Jonathan mss., 1738-1869, consist of letters and papers of Jonathan Williams, 1750-1815, merchant and soldier, grand-nephew of Benjamin Franklin and first superintendent of the U.S. Military Academy at West Point.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Jonathan Williams, 1750-1815, was a merchant and soldier, the grand-nephew of Benjamin Franklin and the first superintendent of the U.S. Military Academy at West Point.
Career: born, May 26, 1750 in Boston; son of Jonathan Williams, merchant, and Grace (Harris) Williams, daughter of Benjamin Franklin's sister, Anne; educated in Boston schools; in 1770 went to London to complete training and to make contacts under Franklin's tutelage; in 1776 joined Franklin in France and was immediately appointed by the commissioners of the Continental Congress to France as their agent at Nantes; became involved in a controversy between Silas Deane and Arthur Lee and resigned as agent, but remained in Europe engaged in various business ventures until Franklin returned home in 1785; married Marianne Alexander of Edinburgh, Scotland, on September 12, 1779; in 1796 became associate judge in the Court of Common Pleas, Philadelphia; served at different times as secretary, councillor, and vice-president of the American Philosophical Society; scientific interests brought him into contact with Thomas Jefferson, who appointed him Inspector of fortifications and superintendent at West Point with the rank of major in 1801; resigned, 1803; reappointed in 1805 with the rank of lieutenant colonel of engineers; planned and supervised the construction of defenses of New York Harbor; resigned from army, July 31, 1812; in War of 1812 served as brevet brigadier general of New York Militia and on a committee in Philadelphia for preparing defenses for the Delaware River; elected to Congress in 1814 but died on May 16, 1815 before taking office.
Arrangement
The manuscripts in the collection have been divided into two chronological arrangements, the first comprising the main body of the manuscripts, 1738-1869, the second being the bills, receipts, checks, notes, etc. The bulk of the latter are for the years, 1790-1814, but there are scattered ones for 1782-1862.
The bound materials in the collection are in a separate series.
Over-size letters and papers and some manufacturer's samples of cloth are in a folio case.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the manuscripts in this collection fall in the period after 1800 and concern themselves with Williams' military service, particularly as Superintendent of West Point and as Inspector of Fortifications. There are many letters and papers relating to the affairs of West Point and numerous letters, documents, plans and drawings of fortifications, coast defenses and harbors of the Eastern United States. There are also a good many family letters, especially correspondence between Jonathan Williams and his wife. Included among these is his so-called "Niagara Journal" in the form of letters from Williams to his wife in the spring and summer of 1801 while he was on a journey to Niagara Falls with General James Wilkinson for the purpose of laying out a road from Buffalo to Niagara and on a trip down the Ohio River.
For the period of Williams' sojourns in England and France there are some accounts, business letters, memoranda, etc., relating to his commercial activities and scientific papers along the line of Benjamin Franklin's interests, particularly those concerned with thermometrical navigation.
Included also are law papers relating to cases before the Court of Common Pleas in Philadelphia of which Williams was an associate judge, notes relating to the court martial of General James Wilkinson, which began on September 2, 1811, at Fredericktown, Maryland, and letters to and from Wilkinson.
Some of Williams' financial records are contained in the collection. Among these are account books, bank books, a cash book, and bills, receipts, checks, notes, etc.
Material connected with Benjamin Franklin includes a journal of a tour made by Benjamin Franklin, Jan Ingenhousz and Williams in 1771 to observe manufacturing and the marble industry in England; letters of Benjamin Franklin to Jonathan Williams, Senior, September 28, 1774, Jonathan Williams, Junior, November 19, 1781, and Jean Louis Girard Soulavie, September 22, 1782, a draft of a "Memoir on Trade" for Dr. Franklin, by Jonathan Williams, Junior, September 15, 1782; a plan for a kitchen fireplace and chimney, 1784, from an idea given to Williams by Franklin; and an undated defense of Franklin's hypothesis for solving the phenomena of light against that of James Bowdoin in a paper presented by Williams to the American Philosophical Society.
For Jonathan Williams, Senior, -1796, father of Jonathan Williams, 1750-1815, and merchant trading to the West Indies, the collection contains records of his transactions as agent for Massachusetts Bay for the Continental lottery of 1776.
Also included in the collection is Benjamin Rush's journal, August 31, 1766-June 23, 1768, as a student at the University of Edinburgh.
Note on Indexing Term - "Art": There are plans and drawings of fortifications, coast defenses and harbors of the Eastern United States.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1944, 1946-1947, 1948, 1950, 1954, 1955, 1981
Art; North America--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Voyages and travels; Science; Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815.; Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815 --Correspondence.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 --Correspondence.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790.; United States Military Academy; United States. Army. Department of West Point.
- Manuscript material, 1738-1869
  Scope and Contents
  The first chronological arrangement comprises the main body of the manuscripts, including correspondence, documents, plans, drawings, memoranda, legal papers, and some journals.
  Correspondents represented in the collection include:
  John James Abert
  John Adams
  John Quincy Adams
  Robert Alexander
  Ethan Augustus Allen
  John Allen
  John Anderson
  George Armistead
  Walker Keith Armistead
  John Armstrong
  Richard H. Ashley
  John Jacob Astor
  Mrs. Sarah (Franklin) Bache
  William Bainbridge
  Edward Bancroft
  Sir Joseph Banks
  Samuel Babcock
  George Baron
  William Amherst Barron
  Lloyd Beall
  Ebenezer Beebe
  Thomas Bennett
  George Cranfield Berkeley
  Charles Biddle
  Clement Biddle
  Clement Cornell Biddle
  James Biddle
  John G. Biddle
  Nicholas Biddle
  Thomas Biddle
  Horace Binney
  George Bird
  Russell Bissell
  John Bliss
  Joseph Bloomfield
  Nathaniel B. Boileau
  Marie V. Boisaubin
  George Bomford
  Phineas Bond
  A.D. Bostwick
  Pascal Vincent Bouis
  Samuel Bradford
  Robert Brent
  Peter Arell Browne
  Daniel Buck
  Daniel Azro Ashley Buck
  John H. Buell
  Henry Burbeck
  William W. Burrows
  Anthony Butler
  Thomas Butler
  F. Cadwalader
  Thomas Cadwalader
  Dr. Carmichael
  John Carter
  Samuel Champlin
  Martin Chittenden
  Auguste Chouteau
  Satterlee Clark
  William Clark
  Henry Clay
  DeWitt Clinton
  James D. Cobb
  Augustus Conant
  Joseph Constant
  Tench Coxe
  James Craig
  John Craig
  George Wahington Cullum
  Thomas Humphrey Cushing
  William Cutbush
  Mrs. Anne Emily (Rush) Cuthbert
  Alexander James Dallas
  L.A. d'Allemand
  Ekaterina Romanovna (Vorontsova) Dashkova
  Henry Dearborn
  Henry Alexander Scammell Dearborn
  Rene Edward DeRussy
  Thomas DeRussy
  Gabriel Duval
  Theodore Dwight
  Grace Williams Eaton
  William Eustis
  Manuel Eyre
  John Roger Fenwick
  Benjamin Field
  Nicholas Fish
  Jonathan Fisk
  George Fleming
  Mahlon Ford
  George Fox
  Benjamin Franklin
  William Franklin
  Constant Freeman
  Nehemiah Freeman
  Benjamin Franklin French
  Robert Fulton
  Edmund Pendleton Gaines
  Albert Gallatin
  Peter Gansevoort
  William Gates
  Thomas Gist
  John Goodman
  Charles Gratiot
  Hyman Gratz
  John Faucheraud Grimke
  Paul Hamilton
  George Harrison
  Ferdinand Rudolph Hassler
  Thomas T. Hewson
  George Washington Hight
  [?] Houqua
  James House
  Daniel Hughes
  Minor Huntington
  J.C. Imbert
  Jan Ingenhousz
  Charles Jared Ingersoll
  Jared Ingersoll
  William Irvine
  George Izard
  Daniel Jackson
  Henry Burbeck Jackson
  Joseph de Jaudenes y Nebot
  William Jones
  Peter P.J. Kean
  Thomas Ketcham
  Lawson Kingsbury
  Henry Knox
  George Latimer
  Benjamin Henry Latrobe
  John Lawrence
  N. Lawrence
  Sampson Lawrence
  William C. Leffingwell
  Thomas Leiper
  Luther Leonard
  Simon M. Levy
  John Leybourn
  John Lillie
  William Linnard
  Henry Brockholst Livingston
  John Livingston
  Robert Le Roy Livingston
  Louis Lorimier
  Pierre Louis Lorimier
  William Lorman
  Robert Lucas
  William MacRea
  William McRee
  Alexander Macomb, 1748-1833
  Alexander Macomb, 1782-1844
  Robert Hector Macpherson
  Mrs. Mary (Rush) Manners
  Jared Mansfield
  Ormond Marsh
  John Marshall
  Milo Masson
  Forimond Masson
  Francis Desere Masson
  Richard Worsam Meade
  James Mease
  Samuel Meeker
  Jonathan Mifflin
  Thomas Mifflin
  Samuel Latham Mitchill
  James Monroe
  Thomas Morris
  Carlos Martinez de Yrujo y Tacon
  James Markham Marshall
  marques de Casa Yrujo
  John Morton
  Gurdon Saltonstall Mumford
  Francis B. Murdock
  Jean Guillaume Neuville
  Juljan Ursyn Niemciewicz
  Abimael Youngs Nicoll
  John Norris
  Robert Weir Osborn
  Nathaniel W. Osgood
  Samuel Allyne Otis
  Alden Partridge
  William Partridge
  Robert Patterson
  William Petty
  Timothy Pickering
  Zebulon Pike
  Zebulon Montgomery Pike
  Charles Cotesworth Pickney
  Ninian Pickney
  John Pintard
  Peter Buell Porter
  Justus Post
  John Hare Powel
  August J. Prevost
  Joseph Proveaux
  John Purdon
  James Ramage
  Theodore Randell
  Edmund Randolph
  Thomas Beverly Randolph
  William Randolph
  Samuel B. Rathbone
  Jacob Read
  Joseph Reed
  John Jacob Ulrich Rivardi
  Erastus Roberts
  Jonathan Roberts
  Hezekiah Rogers
  Erastus Root
  Benjamin Rush
  Mrs. Julia (Stockton) Rush
  Julia Williams Rush
  Mrs. Nancy Rush
  Richard Rush
  Samuel Rush
  Gilbert Christian Russell
  Louis Vincent Joseph Le Blond
  comte de Saint- Hilaire
  Abraham L. Sands
  Adam Seybert
  William Simmons
  Lewis S. Simond
  Benjamin Smith
  James Smith
  Simon Snyder
  W. Spering
  Sir Philip Stephens
  John Stevens
  Amos Stoddard
  William Strickland
  James Strode Sweringen
  Joseph Gardner Swift
  George Talcott
  William Tatham
  George Templeman
  Sylvanus Thayer
  Alexander Thompson
  William Thornton
  Thomas Tingey
  Daniel D. Tompkins
  Joseph Gilbert Totten
  Anne Louis de Tousard
  Uriah Tracey
  Thomas Truxtun
  Thomas Tudor Tucker
  Edward D. Turner
  Antonio Valdes
  Louis Valle
  Christopher Van De Vinter
  A.J. Villard
  Hyppolite Henry Villard
  Decius Wadsworth
  John Baptiste de Barth Walbach
  Samuel Ward
  Franklin Wharton
  Joseph Wharton
  John Wheelock
  Richard Whiley
  Samuel White
  John Wickham
  Charles Wilkes
  John Wilkes
  Mrs. Celestine Laveau (Trudeau) Wilkinson
  James Wilkinson
  Prentiss Willard
  Joseph M. Willcox
  Alexander John Williams Josiah Williams
  Mrs. Julia (Rush) Williams
  Mrs. Mariamne (Alexander) Williams
  James Wilson
  Charles Wollstonecraft
  Eleazer Derby Wood
  James Wood
  John Duncan Wyndham
  Christine E. Zoeller
  - 1738-1774 (Box 1)
  - 1775-1776 (Box 1)
  - 1777-1779 (Box 1)
  - 1780-1781 (Box 1)
  - 1782 (Box 1)
  - 1783 (Box 1)
  - 1784 (Box 1)
  - 1785 Jan.-June (Box 1)
  - 1785 July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1786 (Box 1)
  - 1787 (Box 1)
  - 1788 (Box 1)
  - 1789-1790 (Box 1)
  - 1791 Jan.-June (Box 1)
  - 1791 July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1792 (Box 1)
  - 1793 (Box 1)
  - Wissahickon Road, 1794 Jan. 17 (Box 1)
  - 1794 Jan. 18-Dec. 31 (Box 1)
  - 1795 (Box 1)
  - 1796 Jan.-May (Box 1)
  - 1796 June-July (Box 1)
  - 1796 Aug.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1797 Jan.-Mar. (Box 1)
  - 1797 Apr.-June (Box 1)
  - 1797 July-Sept. (Box 1)
  - 1797 Oct.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1798 (Box 1)
  - 1799 Jan.-June (Box 1)
  - 1799 July-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1800 Jan.-Feb. (Box 1)
  - 1800 Mar. (Box 1)
  - 1800 Apr. 30-May 23 (Box 1)
  - 1800 Apr.-May (Box 1)
  - 1800 June-July (Box 1)
  - 1800 Aug.-Dec. (Box 1)
  - 1801 Jan.-Mar. (Box 2)
  - 1801 Apr. (Box 2)
  - 1801 May (Box 2)
  - 1801 June (Box 2)
  - 1801 July (Box 2)
  - 1801 Aug.-Sept. 10 (Box 2)
  - 1801 Sept. 11-30 (Box 2)
  - 1801 Oct.-Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1802 Jan. 1-19 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Jan. 15-Dec. 1 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Jan. 20-31 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Feb. (Box 2)
  - 1802 Mar. (Box 2)
  - 1802 Apr. 1-15 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Apr. 16-30 (Box 2)
  - 1802 May (Box 2)
  - 1802 June (Box 2)
  - 1802 July (Box 2)
  - 1802 Aug. 1-15 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Aug. 16-31 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Sept. 1-10 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Sept. 11-30 (Box 2)
  - 1802 Oct. (Box 2)
  - 1802 Nov. (Box 2)
  - 1802 Dec. 1-1806 Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1802 Dec. (Box 2)
  - 1803 Jan. (Box 2)
  - 1803 Jan. 31 (Box 2)
  - 1803 Feb. (Box 2)
  - 1803 Mar. (Box 2)
  - 1803 Apr. (Box 2)
  - 1803 May (Box 2)
  - 1803 June 1-20 (Box 2)
  - 1803 June 21-30 (Box 2)
  - 1803 July (Box 2)
  - 1803 Aug. 1-11 (Box 2)
  - 1803 Aug 12-31 (Box 2)
  - 1803 Sept. (Box 2)
  - 1803 Oct. (Box 3)
  - 1803 Nov. (Box 3)
  - 1803 Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1803 (Box 3)
  - 1804 Jan. (Box 3)
  - 1804 Feb. (Box 3)
  - 1804 Mar. (Box 3)
  - 1804 Apr.-June (Box 3)
  - 1804 July (Box 3)
  - 1804 Aug. (Box 3)
  - 1804 Sept. (Box 3)
  - 1804 Oct. (Box 3)
  - Survey of New York Harbor, 1804 Oct. 18-1805 Nov. 6 (Box 3)
  - 1804 Nov. (Box 3)
  - 1804 Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1805 Jan. (Box 3)
  - 1805 Feb. (Box 3)
  - 1805 Mar. (Box 3)
  - 1805 Apr. (Box 3)
  - 1805 May 1-24 (Box 3)
  - 1805 May 25-June (Box 3)
  - 1805 July 1-15 (Box 3)
  - 1805 July 16-22 (Box 3)
  - 1805 July 23-31 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Aug. 1-15 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Aug. 16-31 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Sept. 1-10 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Sept. 11-30 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Oct. 2-Nov. 13 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Oct. 1-15 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Oct. 16-31 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Nov. 1-10 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Nov. 11-30 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Dec. 1-17 (Box 3)
  - 1805 Dec. 18-31 (Box 3)
  - 1806 Jan. 1-15 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Jan. 16-25 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Jan. 26-31 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Feb. 1-9 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Feb. 10-19 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Feb. 20-28 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Mar. 1-15 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Mar. 16-31 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Apr. 1-15 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Apr. 16-30 (Box 4)
  - 1806 May 1-19 (Box 4)
  - 1806 May 20-31 (Box 4)
  - 1806 June (Box 4)
  - 1806 July 1-10 (Box 4)
  - 1806 July 11-24 (Box 4)
  - 1806 July 25-31 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Aug. 1-8 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Aug. 9-19 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Aug. 20-31 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Sept. 1-10 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Sept. 11-30 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Oct. 1-14 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Oct. 15-31 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Nov. 1-10 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Nov. 11-19 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Nov. 20-30 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Dec. 1-15 (Box 4)
  - 1806 Dec. 16-31 (Box 4)
  - 1807 Jan. 1-10 (Box 4)
  - 1807 Jan. 11-31 (Box 4)
  - 1807 Feb. 1-10 (Box 4)
  - 1807 Feb. 11-28 (Box 4)
  - 1807 Mar. (Box 4)
  - 1807 Apr. (Box 4)
  - 1807 Apr. 25-30 (Box 4)
  - 1807 May 1-15 (Box 4)
  - 1807 May 16-31 (Box 4)
  - 1807 June (Box 4)
  - 1807 July 1-15 (Box 4)
  - 1807 July 16-23 (Box 4)
  - 1807 July 24-31 (Box 4)
  - 1807 Aug. 1-15 (Box 5)
  - 1807 Aug. 16-31 (Box 5)
  - 1807 Sept. 1-19 (Box 5)
  - 1807 Sept. 20-30 (Box 5)
  - 1807 Oct. 1-7 (Box 5)
  - 1807 Oct. 8-18 (Box 5)
  - 1807 Oct. 19-31 (Box 5)
  - 1807 Nov. (Box 5)
  - 1807 Dec. (Box 5)
  - 1807 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Jan. 1-20 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Jan. 21-31 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Feb. 1-14 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Feb. 15-29 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Mar. 1-19 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Mar. 20-31 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Apr. 1-15 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Apr. 16-30 (Box 5)
  - 1808 May 1-12 (Box 5)
  - 1808 May 13-31 (Box 5)
  - 1808 June 1-15 (Box 5)
  - 1808 June 16-30 (Box 5)
  - 1808 July (Box 5)
  - 1808 Aug. (Box 5)
  - 1808 Sept. (Box 5)
  - 1808 Oct. (Box 5)
  - 1808 Nov. 1-15 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Nov. 16-30 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Dec. 1-14 (Box 5)
  - 1808 Dec. 15-31 (Box 5)
  - 1809 Jan. 1-12 (Box 5)
  - 1809 Jan. 13-31 (Box 5)
  - 1809 Feb. (Box 5)
  - 1809 Mar. (Box 5)
  - 1809 Apr. 1-15 (Box 5)
  - 1809 Apr. 16-30 (Box 5)
  - 1809 May 1-15 (Box 5)
  - 1809 May 16-31 (Box 5)
  - 1809 June (Box 5)
  - 1809 July (Box 5)
  - 1809 Aug. 1-15 (Box 6)
  - 1809 Aug. 16-31 (Box 6)
  - 1809 Sept. (Box 6)
  - 1809 Oct. (Box 6)
  - 1809 Nov. (Box 6)
  - 1809 Dec. 1-13 (Box 6)
  - 1809 Dec. 14-31 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Jan. 1-10 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Jan. 11-31 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Feb. (Box 6)
  - 1810 Mar. 1-15 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Mar. 16-31 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Apr. 1-19 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Apr. 20-30 (Box 6)
  - 1810 May (Box 6)
  - 1810 June 1-15 (Box 6)
  - 1810 June 16-30 (Box 6)
  - 1810 July 1-15 (Box 6)
  - 1810 July 16-31 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Aug. (Box 6)
  - 1810 Sept. (Box 6)
  - 1810 Oct. (Box 6)
  - 1810 Nov. (Box 6)
  - 1810 Dec. 1-15 (Box 6)
  - 1810 Dec. 16-31 (Box 6)
  - 1811 Jan. (Box 6)
  - 1811 Feb. (Box 6)
  - 1811 Mar. (Box 6)
  - 1811 Apr. 1-15 (Box 6)
  - 1811 Apr. 16-30 (Box 6)
  - 1811 May 1-15 (Box 6)
  - 1811 May 16-31 (Box 6)
  - 1811 June (Box 6)
  - 1811 July-Aug. (Box 6)
  - 1811 Sept. 1-2 (Box 6)
  - 1811 Sept. 3-30 (Box 6)
  - 1811 Oct. (Box 7)
  - 1811 Nov. (Box 7)
  - 1811 Dec. (Box 7)
  - 1812 Jan 1-15 (Box 7)
  - 1812 Jan. 16-31 (Box 7)
  - 1812 Feb. (Box 7)
  - 1812 Mar. 1-15 (Box 7)
  - 1812 Mar. 16-31 (Box 7)
  - 1812 Apr. 1-15 (Box 7)
  - 1812 Apr. 16-30 (Box 7)
  - 1812 May 1-15 (Box 7)
  - 1812 May 16-31 (Box 7)
  - 1812 June 1-15 (Box 7)
  - 1812 June 16-30 (Box 7)
  - 1812 July 1-15 (Box 7)
  - 1812 July 16-31 (Box 7)
  - 1812 Aug. (Box 7)
  - 1812 Sept. (Box 7)
  - 1812 Oct.-Dec. (Box 7)
  - 1813 Jan.-Feb. (Box 7)
  - 1813 Mar.-Apr. (Box 7)
  - 1813 May-June (Box 7)
  - 1813 July-Aug. (Box 7)
  - 1813 Sept.-Oct. (Box 7)
  - 1813 Nov.-Dec. 15 (Box 7)
  - 1813 Dec. 16-31 (Box 7)
  - 1814 Jan.-Mar. (Box 7)
  - 1814 Apr. (Box 7)
  - 1814 May (Box 7)
  - 1814 June-July (Box 7)
  - 1814 Aug. (Box 7)
  - 1814 Sept. (Box 7)
  - 1814 Oct. (Box 7)
  - 1814 Nov. (Box 7)
  - 1814 Dec. (Box 7)
  - 1815 Jan. (Box 7)
  - 1815 Feb. (Box 7)
  - 1815 Mar.-June 26 (Box 7)
  - Papers relating to Jonathan Williams' estate., 1815 June 26 (Box 7)
  - 1815 July-Dec. (Box 7)
  - Notebook, S. Rush, 1818 (Box 8)
  - 1816-1819 (Box 8)
  - 1820-1823 (Box 8)
  - 1824-1829 (Box 8)
  - 1830-1834 (Box 8)
  - 1835 (Box 8)
  - 1836-1840 (Box 8)
  - 1841-1846 (Box 8)
  - 1847-1869 (Box 8)
  - American Philosophical Society papers., undated. (Box 8)
  - Leonard, Gilberto. Testimonial on behalf of James Wilkinson., undated. (Box 8)
  - Williams, Jonathan, Sr. papers, undated. (Box 8)
  - Williams, Mrs. Mariamne (Alexander) letters, undated. (Box 8)
  - Letters to Mrs. Mariamne (Alexander) Williams, undated. (Box 8)
  - Plans and drawings of Philadelphia, undated. (Box 8)
  - Williams, Jonathan, Jr. on slavery., undated. (Box 8)
  - Williams, Jonathan, Jr. To Franklin, Benjamin., undated. (Box 8)
  - Williams, Jonathan miscellaneous papers., undated.; (11 folders) (Box 8)
  - Papers relating principally to the fortification of New York harbor, undated. (Box 8)
- Financial documents, 1782-1862; 1790-1814
  The second chronological arrangement ncludes principally bills, receipts, checks, and notes.
  - 1782 (Box 8)
  - 1784 (Box 8)
  - 1789 (Box 8)
  - 1790 (Box 8)
  - 1791 (Box 8)
  - 1792 Jan.-June (Box 8)
  - 1792 July-Dec. (Box 8)
  - 1793 (Box 8)
  - 1794 (Box 8)
  - 1795 (Box 9)
  - 1796 (Box 9)
  - 1797 (Box 9)
  - 1798 (Box 9)
  - 1799 (Box 9)
  - 1800 (Box 9)
  - 1801 (Box 9)
  - 1802 (Box 9)
  - 1803 (Box 9)
  - 1804 (Box 9)
  - 1805 Jan.-June (Box 9)
  - 1805 July-Dec. (Box 9)
  - 1806 (Box 9)
  - 1807 (Box 9)
  - 1808 (Box 9)
  - 1809 (Box 9)
  - 1810 (Box 9)
  - 1811 (Box 9)
  - 1812 (Box 9)
  - 1813 (Box 9)
  - 1814 (Box 9)
  - 1822-1862 (Box 9)
  - undated. (Box 9)
- Bound materials, 1738-1869 (Box No Box)
  - Account book of house expenses, 1797-1800 (Box No Box)
  - Account book, circa 1799 (Box No Box)
  - Account book, 1790-1791 (Box No Box)
  - Account book, 1800-1807 (Box No Box)
  - Account book, 1803 July 19-1809 Apr. 6 (Box No Box)
  - Bank book, 1796 Oct. 1-1803 Apr. 12 (Box No Box)
  - Bank book, 1812 Apr. 7-1813 July 17 (Box No Box)
  - Bank of New York book, 1804 Dec. 15-1807 Dec. 11 (Box No Box)
  - Benjamin Rush's journalas a student at the University of Edinburgh, 1766 Aug. 31-1768 June 23; (includes original, bound photostat copy, Xerox copy of photostat, copy-flow from microfilm) (Box No Box)
  - Capt. and Miss Manners. Fort Clarence, near Rochester, Kent, England., 1849-1866 (Box No Box)
  - Cash Book, 1799-1801 (Box No Box)
  - Journal of Miss Christine Alexander on a tour of Italy, 1817-1819 (Box No Box)
- Reference materials
  - Benjamin Franklin, Jonathan Williams and the United States Military Academy, Dorothy Zuersher (Dissertation, Doctor of Education, University of North Carolina at Greensboro, 1974) (Box No Box)